<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component type="desktop">
 <id>irscrutinizer.desktop</id>
 <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
 <project_license>GPL-3.0+</project_license>
 <name>irscrutinizer</name>
 <summary>Tool to catch, analyse and create infrared remotes signals</summary>
 <description>
  <p>
IrScrutinizer is a powerful program for capturing, generating, analyzing,
importing and exporting infrared (IR) signals.
</p>
<p>
For capturing and sending IR signals several different hardware sensors
and senders are supported. IR Signals can be imported not only by capturing
from one of the supported hardware sensors (among others: IrWidget,
Global Caché, and Arduino), but also from a number of different file formats
(among others: LIRC, Wave, Pronto Classic and professional, RMDU (partially)
and different text based formats; not only from files, but also from the
clipboard, from URLs, and from file hierarchies), as well as the Internet
IR Databases by Global Caché and by IRDB.
</p>
<p>
Imported signals can be decoded, analyzed, edited, and plotted. A collection
of IR signal can thus be assembled and edited, and finally exported in one of
the many supported formats.
</p>
<p>
In addition, the program contains the powerful IrpMaster IR-renderer, which
means that almost all IR protocols known to the Internet community can be
generated.
</p>
</description>
 <screenshots>
  <screenshot type="default">
   <image>https://leamas.fedorapeople.org/appdata/harctoolbox/irscrutinizer.png</image>
   <caption>The main window showing the application at startup</caption>
  </screenshot>
  <screenshot>
  <image>http://www.harctoolbox.org/repository/scrutinize-signal.png </image>
  <caption>Scrutinize: Identify protocol, timing, repeat patterns, etc</caption>
  </screenshot>
  <screenshot>
    <image>http://www.harctoolbox.org/repository/scrutinize-remote.png</image>
    <caption>Scrutinize remote pane: Analysis and editing of a remote</caption>
  </screenshot>
  <screenshot>
    <image>http://www.harctoolbox.org/repository/export.png</image>
    <caption>Export: signal exporting in a number of different formats</caption>
  </screenshot>
  <screenshot>
    <image>http://www.harctoolbox.org/repository/import-lirc.png</image>
    <caption>Import: remote signal importing in different formats</caption>
  </screenshot>
 </screenshots>

 <url type="homepage">http://harctoolbox.org</url>
 <updatecontact>https://github.com/bengtmartensson/harctoolboxbundle/issues</updatecontact>
</component>

