<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xdoc2html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>The Girr format for universal IR Commands and remotes.</title>
  </header>
<body>
      <table>
      <caption>Revision history</caption>
	<tr>
	  <th>Date</th><th>Description</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>2014-01-28</td>
	  <td>Initial version.</td>
	</tr>
      </table>

<section>
<title>Background and Introduction</title>

<p>There are several Internet sites in whole or in part dedicated to infrared
control of customer electronics. Very soon the question on exchange of IR
signals, individual or as a set of commands from one remote or one device,
comes up. For individual IR signals, the <a href="Glossary.html#CCF">CCF format</a>, also called Hex or
Pronto Hex, is the one most used. This describes <em>one</em> signal, without
a name or any other attributes. To use, the user will most likely have to
copy-paste the information from a downloaded file, or a forum contribution,
into his/her application program. For several signals, this unsystematic
procedure is both tedious and error prone.</p>

<p>Some manufacturers publish the IR commands for their products, often as
tables as Excel list or as PDF documents. There are also some quite impressive
user contributed collections around in Excel format, e.g. for Sony and Yamaha
equipment. Often, these lists contain not only the CCF form, but even a
protocol/parameter form. These lists definitely mark a step in the right direction. With sufficient
skills with the involved tools it is often
possible to transfer a whole set of commands, possibly even preserving names,
with a few clicks. However, this is still a manual process, that is not suited
for automation.</p>

<p>On the other hand, there are a few file formats around, describing a
complete setup of a programmable remote control, like the Philips Pronto <a
href="Glossary.html#ccfFileFormat">CCF file  format</a> or the <a
href="Glossary.html#xcfFileFormat">XCF format</a> of the Pronto
Professional. These describe a complete setup, including layout of buttons and
pages, font selection and other items not of interest for the exchange of IR
signals. The <a href="Glossary.html#rmdu">"device updates" (rmdu-files)</a> of
<a href="Glossary.html#RemoteMaster">RemoteMaster</a> also falls into this
category: They do contain the IR Signals, either as a raw representation or in
a protocol/parameter format, but also a number of key bindings, more-or-less
specific to a particular <a href="Glossary.html#Jp1Remote">JP1 remote</a>.</p>

<p><a href="Glossary.html#Lirc">The Lirc project</a> however has a data base
file format, containing named commands, grouped into named
"remotes". Unfortunately,
the Lirc format was never intended as an exchange format, and, as a general
rule, only Lirc program can read Lirc files. Also, Lirc has a flawed concept
of repeat sequences.</p>

<p>This leads to our mission:</p>
<section><title>Mission</title></section>
<p>To define a universal format for the exchange of IR signals, encompassing
both for protocol/parameter form, and different textual formats, like CCF. The
format should describe the IR signals with their names, (not their
semantics). The commands should be bundled within "remotes". It should be
readable and writable by both humans and programs. The format should  be
free/open for everyone to implement, in open or proprietary contexts. It should
use open technology, so that
tools can be implemented using currently spread free software.</p>

<p>Everyone is invited to implement this format in other programs, or tools for
the format.</p>



<!--p>The present document is intended both as a specification and a tutorial.</p-->
    </section>

<section><title>Program support</title>
<p><a href="Jirc.html">Jirc</a>, which is a translation of substantial parts of
the <a href="http://www.lirc.org">Lirc</a> project to Java, generates Girr
files from Lirc files.</p>

<p><a href="IrScrutinizer.html">IrScrutinizer</a> uses Girr as its preferred format
for import and export of IR signals. It can import and export from many
different file formats and data bases.</p>

<p>My earlier programs <a href="IrpMaster.html">IrpMaster</a> and <a
href="IrMaster.html">IrMaster</a>  generate XML format
output, that is similar, but unfortunately not compatible with Girr. (It can be
considered
as a predecessor to Girr.) However, the distribution contains an XSLT stylesheet
<code>irpmaster2girr.xsl</code> that can be used to translate to Girr
format.</p>

<p>I plan to extend the <a href="Glossary.html#RemoteMaster">RemoteMaster</a>
program (for programming and configuring <a href="Glossary.html#Jp1Remote">Jp1
remotes</a>) with the possibility to export and import Girr files.</p>

<p>I also hope to be able to integrate Girr import into  the <a
href="http://www.openremote.org">OpenRemote</a> project, namely its database
("Beehive").</p>
</section>

<section><title>Copyright</title>
<p>The rights to the described format, as well as <a href="schemas/girr.xsd">the
describing file</a> are in the public domain. That also goes for the present
document. Note that this is in contrast to other documents on <a
href="http://www.harctoolbox.org">www.harctoolbox.org</a> for which no copying
or re-distribution rights are granted, or the therein contained software, which
is licensed under the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.txt">Gnu General
Public License, version 3</a>.</p>
</section>

<section><title>The name of the game</title>
<p>Pronounce "Girr" as one word (not G.I.R.R.), but otherwise any way you
want. It should be used as a proper noun,
capitalized (not uppercase). Preferred file extension is
<code>girr</code>, but this is not necessary. Also, e.g. <code>xml</code> is possible.</p></section>

<section><title>Requirements on a universal IR command/remote format</title>
<p>It should be an XML file determined by an <a
href="Glossary.html#XMLSchema">XML Schema</a>. It should, however, be
usable without validating parsers etc.</p>

<p>The formal rules (enforced by Schema) should be as non-intrusive as
possible, possibly prohibiting "silliness", but otherwise requiring at most a
minimum of formal syntactic sugar. For this reason, it was decided not to use
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xml_namespace">XML namespace</a>, since
it seem to infer another level of difficulty, not only for
defining the language, but also for handling instances and writing tools.</p>

<p>A remote is in principle nothing else than an abstract remote, having a
number of commands. In particular, it should not determine the semantics of the
commands, nor does it describe how to control a device that can be commanded by
the said remote. Names for commands can be "random", in any language, using any printable characters including white
space. A well defined semantic of command names is not granted. However, in
some cases uniqueness in the purely semantic sense is required, for example
ensuring that all commands within a particular remote have unique names.</p>

<p>It can be assumed that all signals consists of an intro-, an repeat-sequence
(any of which, but not both, may be empty), and an optional ending
sequence.</p>

<p>It should be possible to describe signals either as parameterized protocols,
in raw form, or in CCF form. If several forms are present, it should be clear
which one is the primitive form, from which the others are derived.</p>

<p>It should be suitable both for human authoring (with a minimum of
redundancy), as well as machine generation (where simple structure may be more
important than minimum redundancy).</p>

<p>It should be a container format, namely extensible with respect to textual
representation of IR Signals and -sequences.</p>
</section>

<section><title>Demarcation</title>
<ul>
<li>The present work aims at a description for remotes, not devices (e.g. in
the sense of <a href="harctoolbox_doc.html#Device+files">this</a>). Thus,
command names are free form strings, with no semantics inferred.</li>
<li>Only unidirectional "commands" are considered, not data communication.</li>
<li>It is only attempted to define IR signals and "sufficiently similar"
signals. One such signal/sequence consists of a sequence of durations, namely
alternating on-
and off-times. Except for the "normal" IR signals, this includes RF signals of
frequencies 433, 318, 868 MHz etc. used e.g. for controlling power
switches.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section><title>Informal overview of the Girr format</title>
<p>There are four different high-level element in the format:
<code>remotes</code>, <code>remote</code>,
<code>commandSet</code>s, and <code>command</code>s. All can be the root element of a conforming Girr document, although all
software may not handle all of them. Basically,
the element <code>remotes</code> contains one or more <code>remote</code>s,
each
containing
one or more <code>commandSet</code>s, each containing either other
<code>commandSet</code>s and/or <code>command</code>s.</p>
<section><title>command</title>
<p>This element models a command, consisting essentially of a name and an IR
signal, in one or several different representations. Names can consist of any
printable characters including white space, and carries a priori no semantics.</p>

<p>Consider the following example:</p>

<source>
<![CDATA[
<command name="play" displayName="Play |&gt;" comment="" master="parameters">
    <parameters protocol="nec1">
        <parameter name="D" value="0"/>
        <parameter name="F" value="0"/>
    </parameters>
    <raw frequency="38400" dutyCycle="0.50">
        <intro>+9024 -4512 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564
               -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692
               +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564
               -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -564 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692
               +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -1692 +564 -39756
         </intro>
         <repeat>+9024 -2256 +564 -96156</repeat>
    </raw>
    <ccf>0000 006C 0022 0002 015B 00AD 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016
          0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016
          0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016
          0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016
          0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016 0016
          0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 0041
          0016 0041 0016 0041 0016 05F7 015B 0057 0016 0E6C
    </ccf>
    <format name="uei-learned">00 00 2F 00 D0 06 11 A0 08 D0 01 1A
           01 1A 01 1A 03 4E 01 1A 4D A6 11 A0 04 68 01 1A BB CE 22
           01 11 11 11 12 22 22 22 21 11 11 11 12 22 22 22 23 82 45
    </format>
</command>
]]>
</source>
<p>(Details on syntax and semantics are given in the next section.)</p>

<p>In the <code>parameters</code> element, parameters and protocol can be
given. They can be completely given, or they may be inherited from parent
element of type <code>commandSet</code>.</p>
<p>The raw and the CCF form may be given next, as above. Finally, one or may
auxiliary formats of the signal can be given, here
<code>uei-learned</code>.</p>

<section><title>Fat Format</title>
<p>For the ease of further processing of the result, the sequences
within the <code>&lt;raw&gt;</code> element can alternativelly be
given in the "fat" format, where each flash (on-period) and each gap
(off-period) are enclosed in their own element, like in the following
example:</p>
<source>
<![CDATA[
<command name="play" displayName="Play |&gt;" comment="" master="parameters">
    <parameters protocol="nec1">
        <parameter name="D" value="0"/>
        <parameter name="F" value="0"/>
    </parameters>
    <raw frequency="38400" dutyCycle="0.50">
        <intro>
           <flash>9024</flash>
           <gap>4512<gap>
           <flash>564</flash>
           <gap>564</gap>
           <flash>564</flash>
           <gap>564</gap>
]]>
</source></section>

</section>

<section><title>commandSet</title>
<p><code>commandSet</code>s bundles "related" commands together. They may
contain <code>parameters</code> elements, in which case the values are
inherited to children <code>commandSet</code>s and their contained
<code>command</code>s.</p>

<p>Although a <code>remote</code> cannot contain <code>command</code>s
directly &mdash; it must contain a commandSet &mdash; the use of <code>commandSet</code>s is somewhat arbitrary. They can
be used e.g. to structure a remote containing a few different protocols, or one
protocol and a few different device numbers nicely, in particular if hand
writing the Girr file. However, protocol and their parameters can also be given
as <code>parameters</code> within the <code>command</code> element.</p>

</section>
<section><title>remote</title>
<p>A <code>remote</code> is an abstract "clicker", containing a number of
<code>command</code>s. The name of the contained commands must be unique, even
across different <code>commandSet</code>s.</p></section>

<section><title>remotes</title></section>
<p><code>remotes</code>, as the name suggests, is a collection of
<code>remote</code>s, identified by a unique name.</p>
</section>

<section><title>Detailed description of syntax and semantics of the Girr
format</title>
<p>This article describes the Girr format version 1.0, identified by the
attribute <code>girrVersion</code>, expected in the root element of an
instance. (Not to be confused with the version of the <a href="#Supporting+Java+library">support library</a>.)</p>

<p>The <a href="schemas/girr.xsd">Scheme file</a> contains internal documentation of
the semantics of the different elements.</p>

<section><title>Automatically generated documentation</title>
<p><a href="girr-schema-doc/girr.html">Browsable schema documentation</a>
(thanks to Gerald Manger).</p>
      </section>
</section>

<section><title>Stylesheets</title>
<p>A Girr file can be viewed in the browser, provided that it is associated with
a style sheet. This is either a <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cascading_Style_Sheets">cascading style
sheet</a> (css), which essentially tells the browser how different elements are to be
rendered, or an <a href="Glossary.html#XSLT">XSLT style
sheet</a>, which internally translates the XML document to a HTML document,
normally with embedded style information. A description of these techniques is
outside of the scope of the current document (see <a
href="transforming-xml-export.html">this document</a> as an introduction); an example is given as <a
href="stylesheets/simplehtml.xsl">simplehtml.xsl</a>.</p>

<p>To use, add a line like</p>
<source>
<![CDATA[
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="simplehtml.xsl"?>
]]>
</source>
<p>to the Girr file. (Some programs, like IrScrutinizer, can do this
automatically.) Note that some browsers, like Firefox, for security reasons
limits the usage of style sheets to the current directors.</p>

<p>XSLT style-sheets can however be used for other purposes than the name
suggests. Included in the distribution is a "stylesheet"
<code>irpmaster2girr.xsl</code> that translates the XML code from IrpMaster and
IrMaster to Girr format.</p>

</section>

<section><title>Supporting Java library</title>
<p>For importing and exporting Girr files to Java programs, a Java library is
provided. It is documented by its <a href="javadoc/Girr/index.html">Javadoc
documentation</a>. As opposed to the specification  as such, it is licensed under the <a
href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.txt">Gnu General Public License, version
3</a>.</p>

<p>Presently, only import of documents having <a href="#remotes">remotes</a> as
root element is supported.</p>

<p>At the time of writing, the library carries the version number 1.0.0.</p>

<p>The library requires the <a href="IrpMaster.html">IrpMaster</a> classes,
i.e., the <code>irpmaster.jar</code> file.</p>

<p><a href="downloads/Girr-src-1.0.0.zip">Sources download</a>.</p>
</section>


<section><title>Appendix. Parameterized IrSignals</title>
<p>The purpose of this section is to make the article more
self-contained. Information herein are described in greater detail
elsewhere.</p>

<p>The Internet community has classified a large number of <a
href="Glossary.html#IrProtocol">IR Protocol</a>s, see e.g. <a
href="http://www.hifi-remote.com/wiki/index.php?title=DecodeIR">this
listing</a>. These protocols consist of a name of
the protocol, a number of parameters and their allowed domains, and a recipe
on how to turn the parameters
into one, two, or three <a href="Glossary.html#IrSequence">IR sequence</a>s,
making up an <a href="Glossary.html#IrSignal">IR signal</a>. This recipe is
often expressed in the <a href="Glossary.html#IrpNotation">IRP Notation</a>,
which is a compact formal representation of the computations involved. For
particular values of the parameters, a <a
href="Glossary.html#Generating">rendering engine</a> computes the resulting IR
signal, often in <a href="Glossary.html#CCF">CCF, also called Pronto Hex</a> format, or in <a
href="Glossary.html#RawIrSignal">raw format</a>.</p>
</section>
  </body>
</document>
